We have a lot of choices
to make about our diet.
Add to that, doing
the right thing
when it comes
to preventing
and treating a
chronic disease,
fighting a virus,
or losing weight,
and suddenly our
nutrition choices
can seem almost
overwhelming.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we take a look
at the best way
to take care of
the largest organ
in our body: our skin.
In our first story, almonds
are put to the test
in a randomized
controlled trial
for facial wrinkles.
After my video on dates
blew my mind, showing that
eating just a few dates
can significantly reduce
the duration of labor
during childbirth and
improve the
progression of labor.
But there are some surprising
benefits attributed to nuts
in randomized controlled
trials, like how about a study
on the effects of almond
consumption on wrinkles?
Where’d they even
come up with the idea?
Well, population studies
have found that healthy diets
are associated with
less facial wrinkles,
like a meat and junk-
predominant eating pattern
was associated with
more wrinkles, whereas
a fruit-predominant pattern was
associated with fewer wrinkles.
In terms of single foods,
yellow vegetables and soy
appear protective, but
wine may make things worse.
Their thinking is that it
might be the antioxidants
in healthy foods decreasing
the oxidative stress load,
or the anti-inflammatory benefits,
or protection from sun damage,
or improved collagen production,
or better DNA repair.
I have videos on most
of those topics.
The bottom line is
that eating healthier
may reduce wrinkling, which
could actually save lives
if people started eating healthier
to maintain a more youthful
appearance and get all
the chronic disease benefits
as a happy side effect.
Other studies have found the same
thing, supporting recommendations
for more healthy foods like
fruits, vegetables, and nuts.
Here’s another
study that landed on
yellow vegetables,
and greens as well.
In this study, a high intake of
vegetables, beans, and olive oil
appeared to be protective against
spots of precancerous
sun damage,
whereas a high intake of meat
and dairy may make things worse.
Prunes, apples, and tea
seemed particularly good,
but this was a
cross-sectional study,
meaning just a snapshot in time.
Maybe people who eat more meat
are out barbequing in the sun,
or people who eat more prunes
just use more sunblock.
You can’t know for sure if
foods actually affect wrinkling
until you... put them to the test—
but we had no such
studies…until, now.
Why study almonds?
Because it was paid for by
the Almond Board, of course.
The researchers didn’t know
who was in the nut group, though,
and who was in
the control group,
until they were
looking at the results.
The nut group were given
2 ounces of nuts a day,
like two palmfuls of nuts, and
the control group was instead
given nut-free snacks
to eat instead
like nut-free granola
bars or pretzels.
Before and after, they got
high‐res facial photographs
to quantify facial wrinkle
depth and severity using
a computer‐based photographic
analysis and…boom,
the almond group had significantly
decreased wrinkle severity
compared with the control group
by the end of the 16-week study.
The paper concludes:
“Our study demonstrates that
daily almond consumption
may reduce wrinkle severity...”
Now, they used a relatively
large dose, 2 ounces a day,
whereas you can get
cardioprotective benefits
of nuts from even less
than a half an ounce;
so, who knows, maybe they could
have gotten away with using less.
Here’s the low-dose nut
study they referenced,
showing a significant drop in
LDL cholesterol within 6 weeks
eating just a few
almonds a day—10 grams
which is just like
8 almonds a day.
That’s the nice thing
about healthy foods,
they just have good
side effects.
So, global disease prevention
strategies might beneﬁt
from emphasizing that a
healthy diet is also linked
to less facial wrinkling,
and maybe vanity will help us
prevent a few heart
attacks in the bargain.
In our next story,
we discover how
some foods
appear protective
against the development
of skin wrinkles—
while others may
make them worse.
The skin is the largest
organ in the body—
about 20 square feet—
and, the most vulnerable
organ in the body,
exposed to both the oxidizing effects
of UV radiation from the sun,
and the oxidizing effects
of oxygen in the air.
And, years of oxidant
stress can take a toll.
Over the years, skin becomes
thinner, more easily damaged;
loses volume, elasticity,
and can sag and wrinkle.
What can we do about it?
“Skin wrinkling: can
food made a difference?”
They measured healthfulness of skin
using a microtopographic method.
It’s cool; they make a mold of the back
of your hand with a silicone rubber,
peel it off, and then look at it
under a microscope.
This is what young, tight,
healthy skin looks like.
But, then, as we age, our skin
can get all coarse and flaccid.
How can we stop it?
Well, three things contribute
to the aging of skin:
“Oxidative stress…induced by
[sun]-damage, inflammation
and ischemia [lack of
adequate blood flow].”
Oxidative stress means
we need antioxidants.
“Under these circumstances, many
skin antioxidants undergo depletion…
and must be replaced continuously
in order to delay the otherwise inevitable
deterioration which would
lead to skin aging.”
So, plant foods would
presumably help.
And then, inflammation
and lack of blood flow.
And so, one might predict that
saturated fat (inflammation)
and cholesterol (ischemia),
might be associated with
adverse effects on our skin.
Let’s see if our predictions hold up.
“In particular, a high intake
of vegetables, [beans, peas, lentils, soy]
and olive oil appeared to be
protective” against skin wrinkling,
whereas “a high intake
of meat, dairy and butter”
appeared to have an adverse effect.
Prunes, apples, and tea
appeared especially protective.
A recent study, for example,
found that green tea phytonutrients
were able to protect skin
against harmful UV radiation,
and help improve skin quality of women.
After a few months on green tea,
there was a 16% reduction
in skin roughness,
and a 25% reduction in scaling.
Here’s micrographs showing
the reduction in scaling,
as well as improved skin
elasticity and hydration.
Finally today, we
ask the question:
instead of treating
sensitive skin topically,
with lotions and creams,
why not treat it from
the inside out—
with diet?
About half of the American population
says they have sensitive skin,
defined loosely as
“tingling, chafing, burning,”
itching sensations when exposed
to various environmental factors.
A similar high prevalence
has been reported
throughout Japan and Europe—
especially in women.
Often, there are no obvious signs,
and, so, it’s often been dismissed by
the medical community as a
“princess and the pea” phenomenon—
a mindset that has hindered
the investigation of this problem.
But, now, it’s largely
“recognized as a genuine phenomenon
of physiological origin,”
thought to
arise from an
“alteration of the skin barrier allowing
potentially irritating substances
to penetrate the skin and generate
an inflammatory reaction.”
Okay, so, what can
we do about it?
Well, recently, supplementation
of flaxseed oil was found to diminish
skin sensitivity and improve
skin barrier function and condition.
In a randomized, double-blind,
12-week study,
women were given about a half
teaspoon of flaxseed oil a day—
internally—versus safflower oil,
as a control.
That’s the amount of oil found in about
a teaspoon and a half of flaxseeds.
After three months, there was a
significant decrease in skin reddening
in the flax group compared
to the safflower group,
when an irritant chemical
was painted on their forearms
to measure skin sensitivity.
Their skin also ended up
significantly better hydrated,
had significantly better
barrier function—
as evidenced by lower
transepidermal water loss—
skin that’s less rough;
less scaly; and smoother.
You can actually see the changes
in a close-up view of the skin.
Skin looked pretty much
just as dry and scaly
before and after the
safflower oil intervention,
but significantly improved
after flaxseed oil.
Sensitive skin is typically treated by
topical application of lotion and creams.
But, why not treat it
from the inside?
“This study showed that daily
supplementation with flaxseed oil
improved skin appearance and
led to a decreased skin sensitivity
by improving epidermal barrier function
and decreasing inflammation…”
The best source of flax seed oil
is within the flaxseed itself, right?
Then, you get all the nutrition
of the whole food,
and it’s cheaper
and more stable.
Unlike the oil, you can bake with the
seeds without destroying the omega-3s,
and can even store ground flaxseed
for a month, at room temperature,
without spoilage or oxidation.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
Or go to your local public
library for that matter.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.